A Guide to the Fred Orr Wygal Papers, 1881-1980 (bulk: 1950-1980)
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Fred Orr Wygal Papers, 1881-1980 (bulk: 1950-1980)
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 154
5.2 linear feet
Fred Orr Wygal
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Collection was donated to the Department by Mrs. Wygal June 26, 1980
Biographical/Historical Information
Fred Orr Wygal (1900-1980), a leader in the field of education in Virginia, was a native of Dryden in Lee County, Virginia. He received his A.B. degree from Emory and Henry College in 1926 and his M.A. degree from the University of Virginia in 1930. He was named Outstanding Alumnus of the Year by Emory and Henry College in 1967, and he was awarded an honorary Doctor of Humanities degree by that institution in 1974.
Wygal began his educational career as a classroom teacher in Lee County in the mid-1920s, and served as principals of three high schools in Washington and Grayson counties between 1927 and 1939. In 1939, he was named superintendent of the Radford public schools, where he served until 1942, when he was appointed Director of the Division of Guidance and Adult Education for the Virginia Department of Education. He was named Director of the Division of Related Instructional Services in 1954, and in 1958 he became Director of the Division of Teacher Education.
During his years of service with the Department of Education, he took a leave of absence to become acting chief executive of Longwood College during the absence of Francis L. Lankford in 1962-1963. He retired from the State Department of Education in 1964, and became Dean of Students at Ferrum College. He served in this position until 1966, and he again served as acting president of Longwood College from 1967 until 1968. In 1968, he was appointed as acting executive administrator of Virginia Commonwealth University when that University was created by the merger of the medical College of Virginia and Richmond Professional Institute in 1968. He held that post until 1969. In 1968, he was named director of the Virginia Board of Vocational Rehabilitation's study for a proposed long-range plan for vocational rehabilitation. He returned to Ferrum College in 1970.
In addition to his contributions in the educational field, Wygal was a long-time member of Reveille Methodist Church in Richmond, where he taught Young Adult Bible Class for thirty years, and served three terms as Chairman of the Administrative Board. He was also a former president of Rotary International and a former director of the Southern Council of Teacher Education. He was a member of the United Methodist Conference Board of Education, a member of the Richmond Community Council and he was chairman of the Richmond District Committee on Adult Education.
Wygal was honored by three Virginia colleges for his associations with them. The faculty center at Ferrum College, the music building at Longwood College, and the school administration building at Radford University are all named for him.
Wygal was married to Billie Robinson and had one son, Fred O. Wygal, Jr.
Scope and Content Information
The Wygal Papers contain primarily materials related to education in Virginia, particularly higher education, and to activities of the Methodist church. Included in the collection are numerous reports of self- studies conducted by elementary schools in Virginia in which Wygal participated, as well as an investigative study of Radford University. In addition, the collection contains a report and materials related to a self-study conducted by Reveille Methodist Church in which Wygal took an active part.
Wygal's correspondence, both personal and official, provides a clear sense of his commitment to and involvement in the quality of education in Virginia, and much of the material included in the collection is related to his experience in the administration of higher education. Wygal was much in demand as a speaker, both in his capacity as an educator and as an informed layman in his church, and the collection contains over 200 public speaking items, including outlines, notes and texts of speeches and lectures.
Wygal's relationship with the Methodist Church in Virginia was a long and active one, and his influence was felt in many areas of his church's life. The collection contains minutes and related materials of the Administrative Board of Reveille Methodist Church in Richmond, as well as reports and studies of the Wesley Foundation campus ministry at several Virginia schools. Wygal was involved in the Commission for Christian Higher Education, and his papers contain materials related to this activity.
Arrangement
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by series and topically therein.
Organization
Series I--Personal and Biographical (1881-1980)
Series II--Educational Career (1946-1980)
Series III--Elementary Schools Self-Study Reports (1957-1969)
Series IV--Methodist Church Affiliation (1951-1980)
Contents List
- Series I-Personal and Biographical
  - Biographical Information: Fred O. Wygal, Genealogical Information, 1947-1980, undated (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Clippings, 1963-1971, undated (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Letters of Condolence:Fred O. Wygal, 1980 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Correspondence: Personal, 1950-1980 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence: General, 1937-1980 (Box-folder 1:5-1:11)
  - Ephemera, 1942-1974, undated (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Lecture Notes, 1944-1968, undated (Box-folder 1:13-1:18)
  - Speeches and Debates, 1962-1964, undated (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Publication: Virginia's Program for Preparing Better Teachers, 1964 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Association of State Colleges and Universities, Summer Council, 1967 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Scrapbook: Harry H. Styll, 1881-1952 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Photographs, 1951-1960, undated (Box-folder 1:23)
- Series II-Educational Career
  - Teacher Education, 1956-1965, undated (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Teacher Education and Professional Standards Conference Materials, 1965 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Teacher Education and Certification, 1965-1975, undated (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Student Teaching Program in Virginia, 1961-1964 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Virginia Vocational Rehabilitation Resources Project, 1966, undated (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Ferrum Junior College, 1964-1980, undated (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Longwood College: Acting President, 1963-1968 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Longwood College: General, 1946-1979 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Longwood College Personnel: Merle and Emily Landrum, 1964-1971 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Executive Administrator: Virginia Commonwealth University, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Radford College Study Panel, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 2:11-2:14)
  - National Retired Teachers Association: Handbooks, 1973-1977, undated (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Virginia Retired Teachers Association and Virginia Government Employees Association: Retirement, 1975-1980 (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Virginia Retired Teachers Association Bicentennial Committee Report: "Education in Virginia," 1975-1976 (Box-folder 2:17-2:18)
  - Virginia Retired Teachers Association and Related Organization: Retirement, 1969-1980 (Box-folder 2:19)
  - Virginia Conference of Parents and Teachers, 1963-1966 (Box-folder 2:20)
  - Teaching Religion in Public Schools, 1967-1972 (Box-folder 2:21)
  - Race Relations, 1963-1970 (Box-folder 2:22)
  - Course Materials: School-Community Relations, 1948-1967 (Box-folder 2:23)
  - Assorted Education Materials, 1959-1975 (Box-folder 2:24)
  - Richmond District Historical Society, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 2:25)
- Series III-Elementary School Self-Study Reports
  - "Evaluating the Elementary School" by Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, 1964 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Commission on Elementary Schools of the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Instructions for Visiting Committee: Richmond Public Schools Evaluation, 1968 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Self-Study Report: Amelia Street Elementary School, 1968 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Self-Study Report: Baker Elementary School, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Self-Study Report: J. Andrew Bowler School, 1967 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: Chimborazo School, 1968 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Self-Study Report: Ginter Park School, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Self-Study Report: Maymont Elementary School, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Report of Visiting Committee on Major Areas: Maymont School, 1968 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Self-Study Report: Mosby Elementary School, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Self-Study Report: Mary M. Scott School, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Self-Study Report: Westhampton Elementary School, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Self-Study Report: Woodville School, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Summary Report of the Visiting Committees, Nine Elementary Public Schools, Richmond, 1968 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Self-Study Reports: Business Affairs, Richmond Public Schools, 1967 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Self-Study Report: Department of Instruction, Richmond, 1967 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Self-Study Report: Personnel Department Richmond Public Schools, 1967 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Self-Study Report: Pupil Personnel Services, Richmond Public Schools, 1967 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Virginia Elementary Committee: Commission on Elementary Schools of the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, 1969 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Suggested Schedule for Education Committee, Radford, 1969 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Self-Study Report: Kuhn Barnett Elementary School, Radford, 1969 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: Belle Heth Elementary School, Radford, 1969 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: McHarg Elementary School, Radford, 1969 (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: Central Administrative Offices, Radford, 1969 (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Summary Report of the Visiting Committee: Three Elementary Public Schools, Radford, 1969 (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Instructions for Visiting Committees Washington County, Virginia, 1969 (Box-folder 4:13)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: Abingdon Elementary School, Washington County, 1969 (Box-folder 4:14)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: Bethel Elementary School, Washington County, 1969 (Box-folder 4:15)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: Cleveland Elementary School, Washington County, 1969 (Box-folder 4:16)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: Damascus Elementary School, Washington County, 1969 (Box-folder 4:17)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: Glade Spring Elementary School, Washington County, 1969 (Box-folder 4:18)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: Greendale Elementary School, Washington County, 1969 (Box-folder 4:19)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: Hamilton Elementary School, Washington County, 1969 (Box-folder 4:20)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: Hayter's Gap Elementary School, Washington County, 1969 (Box-folder 4:21)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: High Point Elementary School, Washington County, 1969 (Box-folder 4:22)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: William King Elementary School, Washington County, 1969 (Box-folder 4:23)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: Liberty Hall Elementary School, Washington County, 1969 (Box-folder 4:24)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: Meadowview School, Washington County, 1969 (Box-folder 4:25)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: Valley Institute, Washington County, 1969 (Box-folder 4:26)
  - Report of the Visiting Committee: Wallace Elementary School, Washington County, 1969 (Box-folder 4:27)
  - Education in Russia, 1957-1958, undated (Box-folder 4:28)
- Series IV-Methodist Church Affiliation
  - Church-related Correspondence, 1954-1970 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Reveille Church - General, 1951-1980, undated (Box-folder 5:2-5:7)
  - Reveille Church - Budget Reports and Administrative Board Reports, 1957-1980 (Box-folder 5:8-5:9)
  - Reveille Church - Budget Reports and Administrative Board Reports, 1957-1980 (Box-folder 5:8-5:9)
  - Reveille Church - Self-Study Task Force, 1965-1974 (Box-folder 5:10-5:11)
  - Virginia Methodist Conference Materials, 1965-1980 (Box-folder 5:12)
  - Church Lecture Notes and Outlines, 1962-1967, undated (Box-folder 5:13)
  - Wesley Foundation: Longwood College, 1967-1973, undated (Box-folder 5:14)
  - Wesley Foundation: Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, 1973 (Box-folder 5:15)
  - United Campus Ministry: Virginia Commonwealth University, 1969-1979 (Box-folder 5:16)
  - Planning Committee on Christian Higher Education and Campus Ministry, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 5:17-5:18)
  - Virginia Conference of United Methodist Church - Committee to Study the Educational Institutions, 1964-1979 (Box-folder 5:19)
  - Commission on Christian Higher Education and Campus Ministry: Wesley Foundation, 1967-1975 (Box-folder 5:20-5:21)